<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<chapter xml:id="genfun-intcomps" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Products of Generating Functions</title>
	<introduction>
		<p>


	</p>
	</introduction>
	<exercises>
		<title>Practice Problems</title>

		<exercise>
			<title>Generating Function for Weak Compositions of Integers</title>
			<idx><h>Generating Function for Weak Compositions of Integers</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
In this problem, we will use generating functions to prove that
<me>
\frac{1}{(1-x)^k} = \sum_{n=0}^{\infty} {n+k-1 \choose k-1} x^n.
</me>

Recall that a <em>weak composition</em> of <m>n</m> into <m>k</m> parts is an ordered list of nonnegative integers <m>(a_1, a_2, \ldots , a_k)</m> such that <m>\sum_{i=1}^k a_i =n</m> and <m>a_i \geq 0</m> for <m>1 \leq i \leq k</m>.

			<ol>

				<li>
					<p>
 There are 5 weak compositions of 4 into 2 parts. List them.


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Using balls in boxes, find a formula for the number of weak compositions of <m>n</m> into <m>k</m> parts.


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 What is the generating function <m>F_1(x)</m> for the number of weak compositions of <m>n</m> into 1 part?




					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Use the product principle (for generating functions) to find the generating function <m>F_2(x)</m> for the number of weak compositions of <m>n</m> into 2 parts.


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 What is the generating function <m>F_k(x)</m> for the number of weak compositions of <m>n</m> into <m>k</m> parts?



					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Why does this prove that
<me>
\frac{1}{(1-x)^k} = \sum_{n=0}^{\infty} {n+k-1 \choose k-1} x^n
</me>
holds?



					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>



				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>Generating Function for Compositions of Integers</title>
			<idx><h>Generating Function for Compositions of Integers</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
Recall that a <em>(strong) composition</em> of <m>n</m> into <m>k</m> parts is an ordered list of positve integers <m>(a_1, a_2, \ldots , a_k)</m> such that <m>\sum_{i=1}^k a_i =n</m> and <m>a_i \geq 1</m> for <m>1 \leq i \leq k</m>.
In this exercise, we will use generating functions to prove that the number of strong compositions of <m>n</m> into <m>k</m> parts is
<me>
\displaystyle{{n-1 \choose k-1}} \mbox{ when } n \geq k, \mbox{ and } 0 \mbox{ when } n &lt; k.
</me>
(Note:  <m>{n-1 \choose k-1}</m> is defined to be <m>0</m> when <m>n &lt; k</m> because it is impossible to pick more elements than we have. So technically, we  don't need to point this out again.)

			<ol>

				<li>
					<p>
 There are 10 compositions of 6 into 3 parts. List them.


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 What is the generating function <m>G_1(x)</m> for the number of compositions of <m>n</m> into 1 part?


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Use the product principle (for generating functions) to find the generating function <m>G_2(x)</m> for the number of  compositions of <m>n</m> into 2 parts.


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 What is the generating function <m>G_k(x)</m> for the number of  compositions of <m>n</m> into <m>k</m> parts?



					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Starting from the known power series for weak compositions <m>F_k(x)</m>, find the power series for compositions <m>G_k(x)</m>. Hint: re-index using <m>m=n+k</m>.


					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>

				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
	</exercises>


</chapter>
