<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<chapter xml:id="genfun-comp" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Compositions of Generating Functions</title>
	<introduction>
		<p>


	</p>
	</introduction>
	<exercises>
		<title>Practice Problems</title>
		<exercise>
			<title>Organizing Jurors</title>
			<idx><h>Organizing Jurors</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
These two problems use composition of ordinary generating functions. Let <m>{\cal A}</m> be a task with <m>a_0=0</m> and ordinary generating function <m>A(x) = \sum_{n=1}^{\infty} a_n x^n</m>. Let <m>{\cal B}</m> be the task "split the interval <m>[n]</m> into nonempty intervals and perform <m>{\cal A}</m> on each interval." Then the ordinary generating function for <m>{\cal B}</m> is
<me>
B(x) = \frac{1}{1-A(x)}.
</me>


			<ol>

				<li>
					<p>
 Suppose that we have <m>n</m> prospective jurors, each assigned a number. We want to split the jurors into some number of intervals (the first <m>k_1</m> jurors, the next <m>k_2</m> jurors and so on).
			<ol>
\item
Use the composition result above to find the ordinary generating function <m>B(x)</m> for this process. (Hint: task <m>{\cal A}</m> is "do nothing.")


				<li>
					<p>
 Find the value of <m>b_n</m>.


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Give a combinatorial proof of your value in (b). (Hint: if you haven't yet done so, simplify your answer in (b) to a single term.)



					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>

					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Now, once we have split the people into groups, we want to do some further organization. We must choose a foreman, and then the remaining people will be designated as juror, alternate or dismissed. Find the generating function <m>B(x)</m> for the total process (splitting the pool and then assigning roles).


					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>



				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>Organizing Employees</title>
			<idx><h>Organizing Employees</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
These three problems use composition of exponential generating functions. Let <m>{\cal A}</m> be a task with <m>a_0=0</m> and exponential generating function <m>A(x) = \sum_{n=1}^{\infty} a_n \frac{x^n}{n!}</m>. Let <m>{\cal B}</m> be the task "partition <m>[n]</m> into nonempty subsets and  perform <m>{\cal A}</m> on each subset." Then the exponential generating function for <m>{\cal B}</m> is
<me>
B(x) = e^{A(x)}.
</me>

			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 Suppose that we have <m>n</m> employees. We want to partition them into some number of nonempty subsets. Use the composition result above to find a formula for the corresponding exponential generating function <m>B(x)</m>. You should recognize this marvelous generating function.



					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Now, each subset will become a committee, so we need to elect a chair. Give the exponential generating function <m>B(x)</m> for the entire process (partitioning and then choosing a chair for each committee.)



					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Instead of forming a committee, we want to seat each group at a circular table.
			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 Find the exponential generating function <m>B(x)</m> for this process.


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Use <m>B(x)</m> to find the value of <m>b_n</m>. Be amazed at the simplicity of the answer for this complicated question!


					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>
					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>
				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
	</exercises>

</chapter>
