<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>



<chapter xml:id="perm-cycle-structure" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Cycle Structure of Permutations</title>
	<introduction>
		<p>

We quickly review the proof technique of <em>strong induction</em>. The basic framework is:

			</p><p>

<em> Base Case:</em> Typically, you prove the statement is true for <m>n=0</m> or <m>n=1</m>.

			</p><p>

<em> Inductive Step:</em> Assume the statement is true for all <m>k &lt; n</m>.

			</p><p>

<em> Prove True for <m>n</m>:</em> Using the truth of the inductive step (for all <m>k&lt;n</m>), prove that the statement is true for <m>n</m>.

			</p><p>

In (weak) induction, we relate the size <m>n</m> case to the size <m>n-1</m> case. In strong induction, we relate the size <m>n</m> case to the size <m>k</m> case for some <m>k&lt;n</m>. Sometimes this is the more natural way to reduce the problem size.


	</p>
	</introduction>
	<exercises>
		<title>Practice Problems</title>

		<exercise>
			<title>Cycle Decomposition of Permutations</title>
			<idx><h>Cycle Decomposition of Permutations</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
Use strong induction to prove that all <m>n</m>-permutations can be decomposed into a union of disjoint cycles.

<solution>
<p>

		<ul>
			<li>
			<p>
 <em> Base Case: <m>n=1</m></em>

When <m>n</m>=1, there is only one permutation structure: <m>(1)</m>, which is the disjoint union of one cycle.

			</p>
			</li>
			<li>
			<p>
 <em> Inductive Step:</em>

Assume that for <m>k&lt;n</m>, every <m>k</m>-permutation can be decomposed into the union of disjoint cycles.

			</p>
			</li>
			<li>
			<p>
 <em> Prove True for <m>n</m>:</em>

Consider any <m>n</m>-permutation <m>f \in S_n</m>. Suppose that element <m>n</m> has order <m>r</m>. This means that
\[
(n, f(n) , f^2(n), \ldots, f^{r-1}(n))
\]
is a cycle in the permutation <m>n</m>. Considering  remaining <m>n-r</m> elements, we know that <m>f</m> must permute these elements among themselves. In other words, restricting <m>f</m> to these <m>k=n-r</m> elements gives a <m>k</m>-permutation. By strong induction, we can represent this mapping as the union of disjoint cycles. Along with the disjoint <m>r</m>-cycle containing <m>n</m>, we now have a decomposition of the original permutation <m>f</m>.
			</p>
			</li>
		</ul>



</p>
</solution>




				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>A Permutation Identity</title>
			<idx><h>A Permutation Identity</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
Prove the following identity in two different ways:
\[
\sum_{k=1}^{n-1} k \cdot k! = n! - 1 \mbox{ for } n \geq 2.
\]

			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 Give a combinatorial proof of this identity.



			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 Consider a non-identity permutation <m>p_1p_2 \cdots p_n</m>. Let <m>0 \leq j \leq n-1</m> be the  largest integer such that
<m>p_1p_2 \cdots p_j = 12 \cdots (j-1)</m>. That is, the first <m>j-1</m> elements map to themselves, but element <m>j</m> does not map to <m>j</m>. Prove that the number of such <m>n</m>-permutations is  <m>(n-j) \cdot (n-j)!</m>.

<solution>
<p>

Fix <m>j</m> where <m>1 \leq j \leq n</m>. Suppose that <m>p_1p_2 \cdots p_{j-1} = 12 \cdots (j-1)</m>, and <m>p_{j} \neq j.</m>
		<ul>
			<li>
			<p>
 There is one way to assign <m>p_1 p_2 \cdots p_{j-1} = 12 \cdots (j-1)</m>.
			</p>
			</li>
			<li>
			<p>
 There are <m>n-j</m> choices for <m>p_{j}</m> (since we have <m>p_{j} \neq j</m> and the first <m>j-1</m> elements have already been taken).
			</p>
			</li>
			<li>
			<p>
 There are <m>(n-j)!</m> ways to assign the last <m>n-j</m> entries to the remaining <m>n-j</m> elements.
			</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
By the product principle, the total number of ways to create the permutation is
<me>
1 \cdot (n-j) \cdot (n-j)!
</me>
</p>
</solution>


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 The RHS  counts the number of permutations <em>except</em> for the identity permutation. Explain why the LHS counts the same set. (Hint: use part (a), of course!)

<solution>
<p>

If <m>p=p_1 p_2 \cdots p_n</m> is not the identity permutation, then there is some index <m>j</m> such that <m>p_j \neq j</m>. Note that <m>1 \leq j \leq n-1</m> because the value <m>j=n</m> is impossible (if the first <m>n-1</m> elements map to themselves, then so does the last element,

Partitioning the set of non-identity permutations according to the first such index <m>j</m>, we get
<me>
\sum_{j=1}^{n-1} (n-j) \cdot (n-j)! =  \sum_{k=1}^{n-1} k \cdot k!
</me>

</p>
</solution>


					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>



					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Prove the identity using (weak) induction.




<solution>
<p>

		<ul>
			<li>
			<p>
 <em> Base Case: <m>n=2</m></em>

The LHS is <m>1 \cdot 1! = 1</m> and the RHS is <m>2!-1=1</m>.

			</p>
			</li>
			<li>
			<p>
 <em> Inductive Step:</em>

Assume that <m></m>\sum_{k=1}^{n-2} k \cdot k! = (n-1)! - 1.<m></m>

			</p>
			</li>
			<li>
			<p>
 <em> Prove True for <m>n</m>:</em>

<me>
\begin{array}{rcl}
\sum_{k=1}^{n-1} k \cdot k! &amp;=&amp; (n-1) \cdot (n-1)! + \sum_{k=1}^{n-2} k \cdot k! \\
&amp;=&amp; (n-1) \cdot (n-1)! +  (n-1)! - 1 \mbox{ by the inductive assumption} \\
&amp;=&amp; n! -1.
\end{array}
</me>

			</p>
			</li>
		</ul>

</p>
</solution>


					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>

				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
	</exercises>




</chapter>
