<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>



<chapter xml:id="perm-euler-recur" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Cycle Structure of Permutations</title>
	<introduction>
		<p>

We quickly review the proof technique of <em>strong induction</em>. The basic framework is:

			</p><p>

<em> Base Case:</em> Typically, you prove the statement is true for <m>n=0</m> or <m>n=1</m>.

			</p><p>

<em> Inductive Step:</em> Assume the statement is true for all <m>k &lt; n</m>.

			</p><p>

<em> Prove True for <m>n</m>:</em> Using the truth of the inductive step (for all <m>k&lt;n</m>), prove that the statement is true for <m>n</m>.

			</p><p>

In (weak) induction, we relate the size <m>n</m> case to the size <m>n-1</m> case. In strong induction, we relate the size <m>n</m> case to the size <m>k</m> case for some <m>k&lt;n</m>. Sometimes this is the more natural way to reduce the problem size.


	</p>
	</introduction>
	<exercises>
		<title>Practice Problems</title>

		<exercise>
			<title>Cycle Decomposition of Permutations</title>
			<idx><h>Cycle Decomposition of Permutations</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
Use strong induction to prove that all <m>n</m>-permutations can be decomposed into a union of disjoint cycles.





				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>A Permutation Identity</title>
			<idx><h>A Permutation Identity</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
Prove the following identity in two different ways:
\[
\sum_{k=1}^{n-1} k \cdot k! = n! - 1 \mbox{ for } n \geq 2.
\]

			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 Give a combinatorial proof of this identity.



			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 Consider a non-identity permutation <m>p_1p_2 \cdots p_n</m>. Let <m>0 \leq j \leq n-1</m> be the  largest integer such that
<m>p_1p_2 \cdots p_j = 12 \cdots (j-1)</m>. That is, the first <m>j-1</m> elements map to themselves, but element <m>j</m> does not map to <m>j</m>. Prove that the number of such <m>n</m>-permutations is  <m>(n-j) \cdot (n-j)!</m>.



					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 The RHS  counts the number of permutations <em>except</em> for the identity permutation. Explain why the LHS counts the same set. (Hint: use part (a), of course!)



					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>



					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Prove the identity using (weak) induction.






					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>

				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
	</exercises>




</chapter>
