<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<chapter xml:id="graph-exercise" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Graph Exercises</title>
	<introduction>
		<p>





	</p>
	</introduction>
	<exercises>
		<title>Exercises</title>

		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
 .
			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 There are 3 different unlabeled trees on 5 vertices. Draw them all.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Verify Cayley's Theorem for <m>n=5</m> by counting the number of distinct labelings of each of the 3 trees in part (a). Your numbers should add to <m>5^3=125</m>.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 There are 6 different unlabeled trees on 6 vertices. Draw them all.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Verify Cayley's Theorem for <m>n=6</m> by counting the number of distinct labelings of each of the 6 trees in part (c). Your numbers should add to <m>6^4=1296</m>

					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>

				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
 A tree on vertices <m>0,1,2,\ldots, n-1</m> rooted at vertex <m>0</m> is <em>ascending</em> when the label of each child is larger than the label of its parent. For example, there are two ascending trees on 3 vertices:

			<image width="50%" xml:id="fig-img-graph-exercise0">
				<latex-image>
\begin{tikzpicture}

\draw[thick] (-.5, -.67) -- (0,0) -- (.5, -.67);
\draw[fill] (0,0) circle (2pt);
\draw[fill] (-.5,-.67) circle (2pt);
\draw[fill] (.5,-.67) circle (2pt);

\node[above] at (0,0) {0};
\node[right] at (.5,-.67) {1};
\node[left] at (-.5,-.67) {2};

\begin{scope}[shift={(3,0)}]

\draw[thick] (0,0) -- (1, -1.34);
\draw[fill] (0,0) circle (2pt);
\draw[fill] (1,-1.34) circle (2pt);
\draw[fill] (.5,-.67) circle (2pt);

\node[above] at (0,0) {0};
\node[right] at (.5,-.67) {1};
\node[right] at (1,-1.34) {2};

\end{scope}

\end{tikzpicture}
				</latex-image>
			</image>

Use induction on <m>n</m> to prove that the number of ascending trees is <m>(n-1)!</m>.

				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
 Find a closed formula for the number of trees on <m>n</m> vertices with exactly <m>k</m> leaves.

				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
 Let <m>\mathcal{A}_n</m> be  the set of labeled trees  whose internal (non-leaf) vertices all have degree 3. Prove that <m>n</m> must be even, and then find a simple formula for  <m>|\mathcal{A}_n|= |\mathcal{A}_{2k}|</m>.


				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
 Use inclusion-exclusion to find the number of rooted forests on <m>[n]</m> that contain no isolated vertices.

				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
 Let <m>\mathcal{Z}_n</m> be the family of rooted forests such that each rooted component is either (1) an isolated vertex, or (2) a path rooted at one of its endpoints. Prove that
<me>
|\mathcal{Z}_n| = \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} {n \choose k} (n-1)_k.
</me>

				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
 Let <m>T(x) = \sum_{n=1}^{\infty} t_n \frac{x^n}{n!}</m> be the exponential generating function for labeled trees on <m>[n]</m>, where <m>t_0=0</m>. Let <m>F(x) = \sum_{n=1}^{\infty} f_n \frac{x^n}{n!}</m> where <m>f_0=1</m> be the exponential generating function for lableled forests on <m>[n]</m>.
			<ol>
\item
Find a functional equation similar to the one for graphs and connected graphs in \S5.5.3 relating these two generating functions.
\item
Use the <m>x \, D \, \log</m> method to find a recurrence relation for <m>f_n</m>.
				<li>
					<p>
 Give a combinatorial proof of your recurrence relation in part (b). Use the following interpretation: how many ways are there to make a forest with one distinguished vertex (maybe there is a squirrel living there)?
					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>


				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
	</exercises>

</chapter>
